[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is another Ajahn Chah talk.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just simply called Question and Answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a few questions from somebody.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know who that is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, Ajahn Chah answers.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the question... question... first question is...
[SPEAKER_00]: There are those periods when our hearts or mind happen to be absorbed in things and become blemished or darkened, but we are still aware of ourselves.
[SPEAKER_00]: Such as when some form of greed, hatred and delusion comes up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Although we know that these things are objectionable, we are unable to prevent them from arising.
[SPEAKER_00]: Could it be said that even as we are aware of them, this is providing the basis for increased clinging and attachment, and maybe is putting us further back to where we started.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you say that again?
[SPEAKER_00]: Could we say... Could it be said that even as we are aware of them, this is providing the basis for increased clinging and attachment?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is?
[SPEAKER_01]: Their awareness of it or the thing in itself?
[SPEAKER_00]: Being aware of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's providing basis for further clinging.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe it's putting us further back to where we started from.
[SPEAKER_00]: But Ajahn Chah says... Well...
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you read again the question from the start?
[SPEAKER_01]: Let me say it first and then tell me what Ajahn Chah says.
[SPEAKER_00]: So the question begins.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are those periods when our minds happen to be absorbed in things and become blemished or darkened, but we are still aware of ourselves, such as when some form of greed, hatred and delusion comes up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Although we know that these things are
[SPEAKER_00]: Objectionable.
[SPEAKER_00]: We are unable to prevent them from arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the wrong assumption there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Trying to prevent these things from arising, which means not seeing where your responsibility is, but overdoing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Trying to get rid of... trying to prevent things from manifesting in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not on you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That cannot be on you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the response... you're... and that's why they would get confused then, and... and end up revolving around the objectionable states.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they're overdoing the aspect of trying to get rid of it, and that's how you bind yourself with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like a dog that runs around the post, trying to get away from the post.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's tied to the post.
[SPEAKER_01]: Tries to get away from the post, ends up being tighter and tighter, closer to the post.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if that person were to recognize that they can't...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not up to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: To prevent things from manifesting or not, that's not your responsibility, and that's not the problem either.
[SPEAKER_01]: But usually people believe, oh, there is greed in my mind, I must get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is you acting out of the greed, out of aversion, and that's on you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to be able to not interfere with thing that has manifested on its own, and then recognize that you're not responsible for that, and that's not the issue, and that's not the greed in itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the prospect of greed being presented.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's you then choosing to act by body, speech or mind, delighting it, by with mental... delighting in it, welcoming it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's your doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when the Buddha says you shouldn't delight in greed, aversion, delusion, means that you don't delight in what has presented itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: That doesn't mean I must get rid of what has... because that would mean that you are in control.
[SPEAKER_01]: That you are... that you do have a say.
[SPEAKER_01]: As to what appears, what doesn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the fact that if you were to truly have a say, these things wouldn't have arisen in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they do arise on their own, and you have no say, yet you go around acting like you have a say.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you don't know where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you think the problem is in manifestation, and not in the attitude, your attitude towards the manifestation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's where the restraint comes first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not to prevent things from arising,
[SPEAKER_01]: But to enable you to allow things to arise without acting out of... towards them, without acting out of it, out of that pressure of arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the more restrained you are, means the less interfering with things manifestation you would be doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anyway, carry on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anyway, Ajahn Chah answers that.
[SPEAKER_00]: He says, that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: One must keep knowing them at that point.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the method of practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Knowing them and the point of their arising.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then the questioner asks, I mean that simultaneously we are both aware of them and repelled by them, but lacking the ability to resist them.
[SPEAKER_00]: They just burst forth.
[SPEAKER_01]: They can't burst forth unless you act, you choose to act out of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what they don't see.
[SPEAKER_00]: You push them forward.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The pressure might be, yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But no, no amount of the pressure can sort of
[SPEAKER_01]: Make a choice for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always you who chooses to act out of the pressure, which means you can also choose not to act, which means you are the doorway through which the pressure can enter, because you are the one who opens the door, or doesn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not knowing that, then, yeah, it feels like as if the action came automatically out of the pressure, because you haven't practiced restraint sufficiently enough, properly enough, so you haven't discerned that line
[SPEAKER_01]: For which you're responsible, after which, like, you don't cross.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ajahn Chah answers, By then, it's already beyond one's capability to do anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: At that point, one has to readjust oneself and then continue contemplation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't just give up on them, there and then.
[SPEAKER_00]: When one sees things arise in that way, one tends to get upset or feel regret.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it is possible to say that they are uncertain and subject to change.
[SPEAKER_00]: What happens is that one sees these things are wrong, but one is still not ready to or able to deal with them, as if they are independent entities, the leftover karmic tendencies that are still creating and conditioning the state of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: One doesn't wish to allow the mind to become like that, but it does, and it indicates that one's knowledge and awareness is still neither sufficient nor fast enough to keep abreast of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: One must practice and develop mindfulness as much as one can in order to gain a greater and more penetrating awareness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether the mind is soiled or blemished in some way, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: What comes up, one should contemplate the impermanence and uncertainty of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: By maintaining this contemplation at each instant that something arises, after some time, one will see the impermanent nature inherent in all sense objects and mental states.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because one sees them as such, gradually they will lose their importance and one's clinging and attachment to that, which is a blemish on the mind, will continue to diminish.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whenever suffering arises, one will be able to work through it and readjust oneself.
[SPEAKER_00]: But one shouldn't give up on this work or set it aside.
[SPEAKER_00]: One must keep up continuity of effort and try to make one's awareness fast enough to keep in touch with the changing mental conditions.
[SPEAKER_00]: It could be said that so far one's development of the path still lacks sufficient energy to overcome the mental defilements.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whenever suffering arises, the mind becomes clouded over, and one must keep developing that knowledge and understanding of that clouded mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is what one reflects on.
[SPEAKER_00]: One must really take hold of it and repeatedly contemplate that this suffering and discontentment is not just a sure thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's something that is ultimately impermanent, unsatisfactory in itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Focusing on these three characteristics, whenever these conditions of suffering arise, again, one will know them straight away, having experienced them before.
[SPEAKER_00]: And gradually, little by little, one's practice should gain momentum, and as time passes,
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever sense, objects and mental state arise, will lose their value in this way.
[SPEAKER_00]: One's heart will know them for what they are and accordingly put them down, having reached the point where one is able to know things and put them down with ease.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he didn't actually, well, he didn't actually provide a direct answer to the question.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, it's fine, but you could see he was talking around, as in, well, you just have to keep practicing, which is true, but you could have answered it more accurately and point out to a person to start... Like, you can say, oh, you practice and you'll develop wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you can say, well, look for these things and you'll develop wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things such as recognize experience of greed, aversion, delusion in its manifestation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, don't try to negate that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't try to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because by that, by doing that, you're implying the sense of control.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're implying the ownership, the master, you know, this will, this should not be existing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But instead, discern thing enduring in itself, and that's how your attitude towards it will become more apparent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, Ajahn Chah's answer is obviously, you know, there's nothing wrong with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's quite a roundabout way of just sort of telling people, well, just keep doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Telling that person, just keep doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's true, just keep doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But more, more accurately, more acutely, stop trying to get rid of things that are not your responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: And rākuṇa is where responsibility is.
[SPEAKER_00]: He gives a simile.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's go over it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He says, from then on, there will just be arising a passing away in this place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: The same as waves striking the seashore.
[SPEAKER_00]: When a wave comes in and finally reaches the shoreline, it just disintegrates and vanishes.
[SPEAKER_00]: A new wave comes and it happens again.
[SPEAKER_00]: The wave going no further than the limit of the shoreline.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same way, nothing will be able to go beyond the limits established by one's own awareness.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing can enter through that door.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you realize nothing could have ever entered.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Who is going out through the door and being affected by things that are outside.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it was you who was stepping from the shore into the water that's being hit by the waves.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's exactly what I'm talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: You start discerning where your responsibility is and then you don't cross it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you realize the mind can arise in all shapes and forms, whatever it wants, whichever way it wants.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: There never was a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're welcoming it, entertaining it, trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you stop doing that, means that which used to be a basis for acts of greed, still arises.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there is no greed, because greed comes from you, doesn't come from things.
[SPEAKER_01]: That which used to be basis for ill-will, still arises.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there is no ill-will now, in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the waves still continue to come and go, but you don't get wet anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you don't go outside where the waves are.
[SPEAKER_01]: You recognize.
[SPEAKER_01]: And people start going outside, or they carry on going outside, where you don't recognize where the safety from the wave is as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you think I must prevent waves from coming.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the only way to remain dry.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just have to see the range of the wave and allow it to basically express itself, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to recognize things in their manifestation.
[SPEAKER_01]: They have manifested on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: The wave has come on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's you who goes there and tries to push the sea back.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's when you... That's... Basically, that's what person's question implied.
[SPEAKER_01]: How do I... How do I, like, deal with this from arising, so it doesn't arise?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because for him, automatically coming of the waves means automatically me walking into the water and getting wet.
[SPEAKER_01]: He can't see the difference between the two things.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means flood.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means what?
[SPEAKER_01]: It means soaked, drenched.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you were to recognize... No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: The wave can come as like tsunami wave.
[SPEAKER_01]: It still can't cross this line unless I cross it that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where sensory strain will enable you to start discerning that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without sensory strain, yeah, wave means I'm down in the water, either swimming with it or trying to go against it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, actually, the simile is quite accurate.
[SPEAKER_01]: The simile is quite good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because once you start discerning that, it's like finding that a single doorway through which things come in because you invite them in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or that island that no flood can overwhelm.
[SPEAKER_01]: The island that no flood can overwhelm.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or as the Buddha gave the other one, the town that's surrounded by the wall and there is only one point of entry and exit.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize, well, if I want to keep track of what's going on inside,
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't need to chase people who come in and go after people they go out.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just need to stay at the doorway.
[SPEAKER_01]: The doorway of that mindful context, in regard to feeling, in regard to perceptions, in regard to intentions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not the doorway of focusing on the tip of your nose where you're not aware of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's basically like you staring at the actual doorway and you don't see who walks through the doorway, because you're staring at the woodwork of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you want to see, okay, whoever comes in, I know that it's in, because there's no other way of going out.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whatever manifests itself, you know it manifested to this extent, and there is lust in the mind in regard to it, or there is non-lust in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Neither of those things are still a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is when you start entertaining that lust, and then welcoming it, welcoming the prospect of what that lust is pointing at, and that's how you start acting out of the desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you don't act out of desire and ill-will, those things cannot enter your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even when you actually act,
[SPEAKER_01]: Those things can't enter your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why freedom from those things is possible in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Choice is not mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, see, people... You can eventually work your way up, whereby you see the actual present choice as not being able to be owned by you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But until you work your way up in this gradual manner, all you're going to be doing is denying the choice after you made it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's a form of determinism.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you made the choice, but then you say, well, there's no self, so this choice couldn't have been mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it was yours when you were making it.
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you know that?
[SPEAKER_01]: It was rooted in greed, or aversion, or distraction and delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: And whenever there is any of these three, there is the conceit, there is sense of I am, which means it is your choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the better way to go about it, not to kind of deny it in hindsight, but actually take it as a blanket rule, that the choice is always yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, through that sense of responsibility for the slightest choice you make, you can then eventually overcome the ownership of the choice and responsibility with it, not remove the responsibility for the choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in order to... in order to remove the ownership of responsibility, you have to stop denying responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: And people deny responsibility when they say, well, choice is not mine, nothing is mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or people try to deny responsibility when they try to prevent things.
[SPEAKER_01]: They were basis for the choices.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like the question implied.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as Ajahn Chah pointed out, you have to stop... Well, you have to stop engaging with things on that level, but start discerning where you're doing is, and then stop doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's that safe shore you find, that it's inaccessible to these waves.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, these waves remain right in front of you, coming your way at full force, but now you have confidence that they can't cross, because you know that they can't cross.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you stayed with it long enough and you saw that they can't cross.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you haven't stayed with it long enough, well, you still doubt whether they can cross or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, you were affected by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you don't feel safe.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you doubt your safety, you can't say you're safe.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only way to stop doubting your safety is to discern what that safety is in regard to these things that are assailing you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the natural reaction is, I must prevent these things from assailing me in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the true safety.
[SPEAKER_01]: It isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: I must destroy them.
[SPEAKER_01]: I must destroy them.
[SPEAKER_01]: I must...
[SPEAKER_01]: I must remove them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Rather than get to safety.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Rather than actually...
[SPEAKER_01]: Hold on.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't be fighting the sea and the waves and the elements.
[SPEAKER_01]: All I can do is find a place where those elements can't... basically can't set their foot in.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's when nibbāna is that negative.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to maintain it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impossible to maintain it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because maintenance is on the level of intention, choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this is safe in regard to...
[SPEAKER_01]: Remember it?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You discern it in regard to the threat.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it requires no maintenance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because any manifestation is a threat.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means safety is in regard to any threat.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means it's in regard to any manifestation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's the independent manifestation of thing, which is not your doing, that maintains your sense of safety, which is equally not your doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why arahantship is effortless, once you develop it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you only need manifestation.
[SPEAKER_01]: You only need to work, initially, to stop obscuring the true nature of manifestations, that it cannot be owned, because of that it's impermanent, that it's unsatisfactory, because it doesn't have that
[SPEAKER_01]: Sense of pleasure connected with mastery over things.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because of that, it cannot be yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, it's not self.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's always... then that manifestation, discerning a thing, it reveals all the time that safe zone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you fully understood it, you don't have to keep discerning it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only... like an ārya, sāvaka, needs to keep discerning it, because he still has residues of habits of ignorance and lust and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he has to keep going against that grain until it's fully purified and then there is nothing with the grain anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm just saying this so people don't develop... you might... like Arahant is just constantly, this is a manifestation, this is a manifestation... No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever you're aware of, it has been manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: To that extent, you're fully aware of it already.
[SPEAKER_01]: And to that extent, you're fully free from it already.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there was nothing to affect you in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's think, well, and Aryan, then, would... You're aware of it...
[SPEAKER_00]: It reveals the island.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: The island is revealed by the waves.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all you need is...
[SPEAKER_01]: The island is outlined by the sea.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the unborn, like if the sea is born, nibbāna is the unborn, the unmanifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, from whatever is manifested, nibbāna is outlined by being the opposite of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Undefined, undesignated, undetermined.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by recognizing that, you can't unrecognize it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't go back the other way and pretend you haven't recognized it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You haven't recognized the extent of manifestation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that is the true nature of manifestations.
[SPEAKER_01]: They cannot be owned.
[SPEAKER_01]: They cannot be pleasurable.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you cannot be your own.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is the true nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why liberation from the ownership, this sense of self and the dependence on pleasure is possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you actually get to discern and then these things become inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: If those things were not truly
[SPEAKER_01]: Beyond the ownership, unpleasant, not your sense of self, they can't be maintained in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If they were not truly like that, you wouldn't be able to free yourself from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The sense of self would be the master and owner of the experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that means there wouldn't be any problems or suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the fact that there is a problem of suffering, means the sense of ownership is incompatible with that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why human existence is a discrepancy between how things actually are and how you're acting them to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why you're responsible for their being.
[SPEAKER_01]: Discrepancy, dukkha... Any degree of discrepancy determines the degree of liability towards the dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no discrepancy, no base for dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in the scene, there's just the scene.
[SPEAKER_01]: A is just A.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no discrepancy there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, the people sometimes get the sense of it, but then they look for the discrepancy at the wrong place.
[SPEAKER_01]: They look at the discrepancy in the A.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they try to resolve A of discrepancy.
[SPEAKER_01]: The scene must be resolved of the lust, and aversion, delusion, of the discrepancy of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Lust, and aversion, delusion is not in the scene.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's in your attitude towards it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where you remove that kind of attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: You undo it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You extinguish it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then what you have is in the scene, there's just the scene.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the herd, there's just the herd.
[SPEAKER_00]: Smell, taste, touch, same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thought, thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what person's question implied is, oh, there is a scene of greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: How do I prevent it from being seen?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he didn't see, he doesn't see that the issue was in his attitude towards the scene, not the scene.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, his question of trying to deal with the scene, prevent it, make it not, make it unmanifest,
[SPEAKER_00]: Here is another Ajahn Chah talk called Clarity of Insight.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's just one paragraph from that talk.
[SPEAKER_00]: So he says, Ajahn Chah says, the investigation and development of insight into the dhamma gives rise to this profound peace of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having gained such clear and penetrating insight means it is sustained at all times, whether you are sitting meditation, with your eyes closed, or even if you are doing something with your eyes open.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever situation you find yourself in, be it in formal meditation or not, the clarity of insight remains.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you have unwavering mindfulness of the mind, within the mind, you don't forget yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether standing, walking, sitting or lying down, the awareness within makes it impossible to lose mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a state of awareness that prevents you forgetting yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mindfulness has become so strong that it is self-sustaining to the point where it becomes natural for the mind to be that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or as they say, effortless.
[SPEAKER_00]: Effortless.
[SPEAKER_00]: These are the results of training and cultivating the mind and it is here where you go beyond doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have no doubts about the future.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have no doubts about the past.
[SPEAKER_00]: And accordingly, have no need to doubt about the present either.
[SPEAKER_00]: You still have awareness that there is such a thing as past, present and future.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are aware of the existence of time.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is the reality of the past, present and future.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you are no longer concerned, worried about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why I keep saying it's real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, people would say, oh, you must stop thinking about, stop planning about the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Time is just a construction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So what?
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's real as a construction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your past is real as such in the present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your future plans are real as such in the present.
[SPEAKER_01]: You, you saying, you must not worry about the future, is you worrying about the future while you're saying you should not worry about the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're clearly saying, I must not plan the future, and you're planning to do that, to not plan the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're contradicting yourself within that same sentence.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why you're wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you realize, well, whether you think about the past or you think about the future, you cannot do that any differently than in the present.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you're aware, if you're mindful of that inescapable,
[SPEAKER_01]: To let go of the past, let go of the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can do that only on the basis of the presently enduring experience of whatever that experience is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this unwavering mindfulness?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that would be the unwavering mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mindfulness that doesn't chase the content of your past, the content of the future, or tries to get super absorbed in the content of the present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Instead, it recognizes, well, whether I want this to be or not, it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has a reason and it's persisting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any movement I make in regard to it, whether towards it, away from it, towards the past, towards the future, it's only on the basis of this thing still be... of this experience still being there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I'm not saying that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You start being mindful of that, that fundamental peripheral context that, oh, all my movements and motions and plans and, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: Intentions, feelings, even perceptions in that manner, are on the basis of this thing still being there.
[SPEAKER_01]: This experience still enduring on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: You start discerning that, you start developing mindfulness on the right level.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's effortless.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is unwavering, because it doesn't... the context doesn't waver in regard to its content.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's other way around.
[SPEAKER_01]: The content gets its meaning from the context.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I think, you know, there's a difference between mindfulness and awareness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's, it's, it's, it's, it comes together, mindfulness and awareness.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't separate it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you could think of awareness as being more acutely mindful, and mindfulness as being mindful through and through, whether acutely or broadly, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, mindfulness and awareness, it goes hand in hand.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sati, sampajañña.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in practical terms, I guess, like, I don't know, I can take an example of... Well, say like this, you, you, you, like the future example we gave, like you're worrying about something that's going to happen in two or three days, but your worry is right in the present.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to wait for three days to experience the worry on account of a future prospect.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're experiencing it right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: In regard to the future prospect.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as such, that future prospect is real.
[SPEAKER_01]: As future.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is present to you as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why you can be concerned about the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you can still grieve over the past.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't escape it, in other words.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're looking at the content of your future or content of the past, you're bound by it in the present.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you have no choice about that.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're looking at the content of your present, you're bound by it in the present.
[SPEAKER_01]: You realize that was never the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things that happened to you in the past, the content of experiences that happened to you, good or bad, traumas or blessings, whatever, the content of the future prospect that might happen to you, some of it will happen to you, you have no say in that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that was never the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem was that in the present, you were exposed to suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even the future dukkha is presently felt.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, from that point of view, dukkha is always in the present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, when you think about a future pain, it's painful right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: It touches you right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: You presently can free yourself from liability to future suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you're actually waiting for the future content, then you can't free yourself right here and now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that has presently manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you understand it on that level, that that's where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the problem is not in two or three days what's going to happen to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is that you are affected by it now.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you find a way to not be affected by it now, you won't worry about it in three days' time either.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like that, say, meta-meditation, where you imagine meeting
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's it's along the right lines, but it's not quite accurate, because you need to know what, like, the problem is not the person, the problem is not meeting them or not meeting them.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is, you are trying to presently, right here, right now, get rid of the unpleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's always the root of the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Resistance to the displeasure, craving for pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you think about the future prospect, meeting somebody in three days, that always upsets you and hurts you,
[SPEAKER_01]: That thing touches you, not because you meet that person, or you will meet it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That thing touches you because you're trying to get rid of that prospect right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why you suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why four noble truths are always in the present.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the present insight.
[SPEAKER_01]: One insight of craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Presence of craving means presence of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if I suffer now, means I crave now.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't crave in three days time, or I don't crave in ten years ago.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, I've done it back then, and I probably will do it in the future, if I don't become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: But craving is always in the present.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why suffering is always in the present.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why if you approve that, none of your past changes, and none of your future needs to change either.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's why you can't worry on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not that you don't worry about the future or grieve over past, because you're so focused hard on the present moment that nothing else exists.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's usually what people hope to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: I focus, focus, focus, still I narrow my field of vision, so I don't see anything before or after.
[SPEAKER_01]: Failing to see that no matter how much you narrow it, before and after are always implied in the present moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whether your present moment is narrow or wide, there is past, there is future within it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're just trying to shut it down by trying to narrow on the content of whatever's in front of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's usually what people think meditation is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Focusing, focusing, focusing, focusing, so I kind of lose the sight of my past problems and don't overthink future issues.
[SPEAKER_01]: But once you realize that it doesn't matter if you... if you still think about the past or if you're overthinking the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is never in those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is in you, currently, right here, right now, persisting in an attitude of not wanting disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Be it past, be it future, be it present.
[SPEAKER_01]: You remove the not wanting of disagreeable, that doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, in three days, I will meet this disagreeable person.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I'm not trying to get rid of the disagreeability of that future prospect right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it doesn't matter what future awaits?
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter what I do.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter what I say.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't need to plan my actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't need to rehearse my behavior.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't need to go through psychotherapy counseling sessions to plan how I will act in the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: All I need to do
[SPEAKER_01]: is not crave presently to get rid of the equally present prospect of disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how future is in the present already.
[SPEAKER_01]: Past is in the present.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why previous issues, they used to bother you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You used to grieve over things that happened in the past.
[SPEAKER_01]: You kept grieving over it for years.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you will stop.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because grieving is always in the present.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, literally, it doesn't matter what happened to you in the past.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will be unable to grieve over it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like the examples in the suttas of that lady whose husband died, children got one drowned, the other killed by jackals, reached the village, parents, earthquake, roof fell, killed them.
[SPEAKER_01]: She lost everyone in a course of one night.
[SPEAKER_01]: And she went mad, basically, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's like the epitome of the traumatized experience you can imagine.
[SPEAKER_01]: And she met the Buddha, got the teaching, practiced, became an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: None of that changed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Her loss hasn't changed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Her previous griefs haven't changed.
[SPEAKER_01]: But she cannot grieve over it anymore presently, which is always where the suffering was.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, again, it comes to that simile again, being an island.
[SPEAKER_00]: Being an island, yep.
[SPEAKER_00]: What future, what waves come, memories of the past, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's only your lack of clarity in regard to that, that sort of makes you affected by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not discerning truly what an island is.